Jason M. Bryer, Ph.D.

Professional Interests

Teaching and research within K-12 and higher education. Specific areas of interest include the use of technology (e.g. R and LaTeX) for reproducible research; academic self-regulated learning; formative assessment; issues of social justice and equity in education; and methodological and statistical topics, particularly propensity score analysis and modern graphics.

Education

2014 **Ph.D.**, *University at Albany*, Albany, NY.

Educational Psychology & Methodology

2009 M.S., University at Albany, Albany, NY.

Educational Psychology & Methodology

2004-2005 Coursework Completed, The College of Saint Rose Graduate School, Albany, NY.

Adolescent Education in Mathematics

1999 **B.A.**, The College of Saint Rose, Albany, NY.

Mathematics major; Computer Information Systems minor

Dissertation

Title A National Study Comparing Charter and Traditional Public Schools Using Propensity

Score Analysis

Committee Robert M. Pruzek (chair), Bruce Dudek (co-chair), Heidi Andrade, Kathryn S. Schiller

Website https://github.com/jbryer/Dissertation

Professional Experiences

2016-present Executive Director & Principal Investigator, Excelsior College, Albany, NY.

Manage FIPSE First in the World grant to develop a Diagnostic Assessment and Achievement of College Skills (DAACS; \$2,999,877). DAACS provides incoming students with realtime, actionable feedback about their strengths and weaknesses in critical college skills including self-regulation, math, reading, and writing. Additionally, DAACS provides critical information for predictive analytics at the college.

Website: http://www.DAACS.net

- 2015-present Adjunct Associate Professor, CUNY School of Professional Studies, New York, NY.
 Courses taught: IS 606 Statistics & Probability for Data Analytics (Summer 2015, Fall 2015, Spring 2016, Fall 2016)
- 2015-present Consultant / Learning Analyst, NYS PBIS Technical Assistance Center, Albany, NY.

 Developed a data system to support Behavior Specialists work with schools within New York State on their implementation of Positive Behavior Interventions and Supports (PBIS). The goal of this website is to consolidate disparate data sources along with custom data entry so that Behavior Specialists can make data based decisions. I also provided statistical support for analyzing the data at the state level. Website: http://pbisny.org
 - 2014-2015 **Director of Research & Project Evaluation**, *Excelsior College*, Albany, NY.

 Assisted the College in seeking external grants and provide research support for existing grants.

Assisted the College in seeking external grants and provide research support for existing grants. Significant activities included:

- **Principal Investigator** for a Gates Foundation funded grant (\$168,572) on the use of adaptive learning technology in Biology and Mathematics.
- **Lead Evaluator** for New York State Higher Education Services Corporation (HESC) grant (\$449,438) for the expansion of the Online Writing Lab to NYS Community Colleges.
- 2009-2015 **Adjunct Instructor**, University at Albany, Division of Educational Psychology & Methodology, Albany, NY.

Courses taught: EPSY 420 Child & Adolescent Development (Fall 2008, Spring 2009), EPSY 530 Statistics I (Fall 2013, Summer 2014, Fall 2014, Summer 2015), EPSY 887 Computational Statistics (Spring 2013), EPSY 887 Data Science Institute (Fall 2014)

- 2008-2014 **Senior Research Analyst**, *Excelsior College*, *Office of Institutional Research*, Albany, NY. Conducted research and data analysis related to the College's mission. This includes developing, administering, and analyzing surveys; analyzing data from the college's student information system; and consulting with individual schools to develop specific measures. I also provided substantial support and training for other Research Analysts within the Office covering topics such as methodology, statistics, and reproducible research.
- 2008-2010 **Research Assistant**, Head Start University Partnership for Classroom Quality, Albany, NY.

Assisted with data collection, entry, maintenance, and analysis to evaluate the effectiveness of behavioral (Positive Behavior Support [PBS]) and literacy interventions using the Response-to-Intervention (RTI) model.

Principal investigators: Kevin P. Quinn & Frank R. Vellutino

- 2008-2011 **Webmaster**, *University at Albany, School of Education*, Albany, NY. Developed and maintained all School of Education websites.
- 2006-2007 **Graduate Assistant**, *Teaching Mathematics for Understanding, University at Albany*, Albany, NY.

Developed and led planning sessions with K-8 mathematics teachers in urban school districts on social justice topics in the mathematics curriculum. Assisted in other areas of the project including data collection, conference planning, and development of online professional development courses. Principal Investigators: Abbe Herzig & Vicky Kouba

- 2006-2008 **Senior Applications Developer**, *Excelsior College*, Albany, NY.

 Developed Java applications for distance learning and student management systems.
- 2004-2006 **Senior Software Engineer**, *State University of New York*, Albany, NY.

 Developed web based applications in Java and related technologies as part of a state wide financial and human resource systems.

1999-2004 **Software Engineer**, *MapInfo*, Troy, NY.

Contributed key features as part of a geographic information system (GIS) server application (MapX-treme Java) including API for reading and writing binary GIS data, framework for web based applications, and data binding.

1997-1999 **Web Developer**, Office of the Attorney General, Albany, NY.

Software developer and website designer for the New York State Attorney General's Website.

Teaching Experiences

Spring 2017 Fall 2016 **DATA 606 Statistics and Probability for Data Analytics** (CUNY School of Professional Studies)

Spring 2016 Fall 2015 Summer 2015

This course covers basic techniques in probability and statistics that are important in the field of data analytics. Discrete probability models, sampling from infinite and finite populations, statistical distributions, basic Bayesian statistics, and non-parametric statistical techniques for categorical data are covered in this course. Each of these statistical concepts will be applied in a variety of real-world scenarios through the use of case studies and customized data sets.

Course page: http://DATA606.net

Summer 2015

EPSY 530 Statistics I (University at Albany)

Fall 2014 Summer 2014 Descriptive statistics including measures of central tendency and variability, correlation and regression. Introduction to statistical inference, including sampling distributions, significance tests, confidence intervals, and power of tests of significance.

Fall 2013

Course website: http://epsy530.bryer.org

Fall 2014

EPSY 887 Data Science Institute (University at Albany)

Data Science is the intersection of statistics, computer science, and research. This seminar will introduce the key concepts of data science with an emphasis on data science in education. We will cover the important statistical and programming concepts necessary for conducting reproducible research on large datasets. The open source program R will be used throughout the course. No programming experience is required but at least two semesters of graduate statistics is highly recommended.

Course website: https://github.com/jbryer/EPSY887DataScience

April/May 2014

Applied Propensity Score Analysis with R (Workshop given at the University at Albany) This two day workshop provided an introduction to propensity score methods using R as well as more advanced topics including multilevel PSA, non-binary treatment matching, and bootstrapping. Workshop website: http://psa.bryer.org

Spring 2013

EPSY 887 Institute in Education: Computational Statistics (University at Albany)

This seminar will provide an introduction to statistical programming for data analysis with an emphasis on the analysis of large datasets. With the increased availability of large national and international datasets (e.g. PISA, TIMMS, NAEP, ECLS) there is a great opportunity and potential for researchers to address important questions. However, the analysis of large datasets requires special analytical procedures not found in commercial statistics software. Utilizing the open source statistical software R, students will be introduced to the tools and procedures for analyzing large datasets with an emphasis on conducting transparent and reproducible research.

Course website: https://github.com/jbryer/CompStats

Introduction to Propensity Score Methods with R (useR! 2013 Pre-Conference Work-July 2013 shop) This workshop will provide participants with a theoretical overview of propensity score methods as well as illustrations and discussion of PSA applications using R. Fall 2016 Introduction to R and LaTeX for Institutional Research (Workshop given at the Fall 2015 Northeast Association for Institutional Research) Fall 2013 This workshop provides an overview as well as hands-on exercises for using R and LaTeX to perform Fall 2012 data analysis and report generation. Participants learn to perform basic statistical analyses in R Fall 2011 and to generate reports with LaTeX in spreadsheet, presentation, and document formats. Spring 2009 **EPSY 420 Child & Adolescent Development** (University at Albany) Fall 2008 This course covers theory and research in social, emotional, physical, and intellectual development and its application to instruction with an emphasis on late childhood through middle adolescence. 2007-2012 Assisted in teaching the online section of Statistics I (EPSY 530) including the installation Fall Semesters and management of the Moodle Content Management System (moodle.bryer.org). Service Positions Founding Organizer of the Albany R Users Group 2014-present Website: http://www.meetup.com/Albany-R-Users-Group **Dissertation Committees** 2016 Kimberly Speershneider - The Differentiated Impact Of Early Entry Into Head Start On Social Competence And Literacy: An Applied Propensity Score Analysis 2015 Chrisopher Valle - Effects Of Criteria-Referenced Formative Assessment On Achievement In Music 2015 Fei Chen - The Impact of Criteria-Referenced Formative Assessment On Fifth Grade Students' Theater Arts And English Language Arts Achievement

	Excelsior College
2015-present	Chair, Diagnostic Assessment & Achievement of College Skills Advisory Committee
2014-present	Chair, Technology Advisory Subcommittee
2014-present	Committee Member, Information Technology Committee
2013-2014	Committee Member, Persistence Measure Task Force
2010-2014	Committee Member, Student Learning Support Services Committee
2010-2014	Committee Member, Data Definitions & Quality
2010-2013	Committee Member, Information Technology Operations & Security Committee
2011-2012	Committee Member, Search Committee for Assistant Provost
2009-2010	Committee Member, Early Alert System for Identifying Non-Persistent Students
2009	Chair, Task Force on a Library of Model Courses
2009-2010	Committee Member, System for Storing Information at Excelsior College
	City School District of Albany
	City School District of Albany
2011-2012	Committee Member, Grade Configuration Committee; Chair of the Accountability Subcommittee

American Educational Research Association

2009-2011	Treasurer,	Studying	and	Self-Regulated	Learning	Special	Interest	Group

2009-2010 Committee Member, Division D Membership Committee

University at Albany, Division of Educational Psychology & Methodology

2007-2008 Treasurer, Graduate Student Organization

Professional Memberships

AERA American Edu	cational Researd	h Association
-------------------	------------------	---------------

- AIR Association for Institutional Research
- ASA American Statistical Association
- NEAIR North East Association for Institutional Research
- NCME National Council on Measurement in Education

Awards & Grants

- 2015-2019 **Principal Investigator** FIPSE First in the World grant (\$2,999,877, P116F150077), *Diagnostic Assessment & Achievement of College Skills: Personalized Feedback & Targeted Student Supports.*
- 2013-2015 **Principal Investigator** Bill & Melinda Gates Foundation grant (\$168,572) on the use of adaptive learning technology in introductory Biology and Mathematics courses.
- 2014-2016 **Lead Evaluator** for a New York State Higher Education Services Corporation (HESC) grant (\$449,438) for the expansion of the Online Writing Lab to NYS Community Colleges.
 - 2013 North East Association for Institutional Research (NEAIR) Ambassador Grant (\$800)
 - 2013 Excelsior College, Employee Recognition Award for Excellence in Innovation
- 2011, 2012 The Society of Multivariate Experimental Psychology (SMEP), Workshop Travel Award (three separate awards of \$1,000 each)
 - 2011 National Center for Educational Statistics Workshop Travel Award (~\$800)
 - 2009 Association for Institutional Research (AIR) & National Center for Educational Statistics (NCES), Travel Grant (\$330)
 - 2009 National Science Foundation, Travel/Research Grant (\$1,000)
 - 2009 University at Albany Graduate Student Organization, Travel/Research Grant (\$320.00)
 - 2001 Award for Outstanding Performance, MapInfo.
 - 1999 Sister Noel Marie Cronin Award for excellence in Mathematics, College of Saint Rose.
 - 1999 Outstanding Senior Award for Mathematics/Computer Information Systems, College of Saint Rose.
- 1998, 1999 Service and Appreciation Award, College of Saint Rose.

Professional Development Coursework

- 2015 Targeted Learning, Sherri Rose, Atlantic Causal Inference Conference short course.
- 2014 Applied Predictive Modeling in R, Max Kuhn, useR! Pre-Conference workshop.
- 2013 Using Spatial Data, Roger Bivand, useR! Pre-Conference workshop.
- 2012 Statistical Modeling in the R Context, Bill Venables, useR! Pre-Conference workshop.
- 2012 Geospatial Data in R and Beyond, Barry Rowlingson, useR! Pre-conference workshop.
- 2012 Building R Web Applications with Rook, Jeffry Horner, useR! Pre-conference workshop.
- 2012 Using the School Attendance Boundary Information System (SABINS), Salvatore Saporito and David Van Riper, AERA Mini-Course.
- 2011 R Development Master Class, Hadley Wickham
- 2011 Fitting and Evaluating Mixed Models using lme4, Douglas Bates.
- 2011 National Assessment of Educational Progress (NAEP) Database training, National Center for Educational Statistics.
- 2011 Presenting Data and Information, Edward Tufte.
- 2010 Handling missing data in R with MICE, Karin Groothuis-Oudshoorn and Stef van Buuren, useR!
- 2010 Elastic-R, a google docs-like portal for data analysis in the cloud, Karim Chine, useR!
- 2009 Using IPEDS Data for Institutional Effectiveness, Mary Ann Coughlin, NEAIR Workshop.
- 2009 Accessing and Analyzing National Databases in Secondary and Higher Education, Terrell L. Strayhorn, AERA Extended Course.
- 2009 An Introduction to Hierarchical Linear Modeling with R, J. Kyle Roberts, AERA Mini-Course.
- 2008 An Introduction to Propensity Score Analysis, Robert M. Pruzek, University at Albany.
- 2008 An Introduction to GIS for Educational Researchers, Mark Hogrebe, Courtney A. Bell, & Charisse A. Gulosino, AERA Mini-Course.
- 2008 Foregrounding Issues of Equity and Diversity in Mathematics Education Research: Implications for Research Methods and Teacher Development, Ban Battey, et al., AERA Mini-Course.
- 2008 A "Gentle" Introduction to Statistical Analysis and Teaching with R, Brandon K. Vaughn, AERA Mini-Course.

Graduate Coursework

Completed at the University at Albany

EPSY 522	Adolescent Development
EPSY 530	Statistical Methods I
EPSY 540	Assessment in Education
EPSY 610	Advanced Educational Psychology: Learning & Instruction
EPSY 623	Advanced Developmental Psychology
EPSY 630	Statistical Methods II
EPSY 640	Educational & Psychological Measurement
EPSY 687	Institute in Education: Item Response Theory
EPSY 713	Self-Regulated Learning
EPSY 721	Comparative Theories in Human Development
EPSY 725	Seminar in Human Development: Language Development
ECPY 725	Multivariate Applications in Counseling Psychology
ECPY 726	Analysis of Covariance Structures
EPSY 735	Seminar in Statistics (PSA, bootstrapping, factor analysis)
EPSY 761	History & Issues in Special Education
EAPS 762	Seminar in Advanced Research Methods for Educational Leadership (HLM)
EPSY 780	Seminar in the Profession of Educational Psychology
ETAP 850	Equity, Diversity, & Social Justice in Mathematics & Science Education
EPSY 887	Institute in Education: The Use of R in Educational Psychology
EPSY 887	Institute in Education: Modern Graphics for Social Science Research
	Completed at the College of Saint Rose
EDU 506	Educational Foundations
EDU 530	Middle School Education: Theory & Practice
EDU 590	Research Seminar
EPY 500	Educational Research
EPY 502	Survey of Educational Psychology
SEC 515	Curriculum & Instruction in Secondary Schools
SEC 518	Literacy Improvement in Secondary Schools
SEC 522	Methods of Teaching Math in Secondary Schools

References

Bruce Dudek, Ph.D.

Professor, Department of Psychology

Email bruce.dudek@albany.edu

Phone (518) 442-4824

Address Social Sciences 327

University at Albany 1400 Western Ave Albany, NY 12222

Lisa Daniels, Ph.D.

Assistant Vice President

Email Idaniels@excelsior.edu

Phone (518) 608-8398

Address 7 Columbia Circle

Albany, NY 12203-5159

Heidi Andrade, Ed.D.

Associate Dean for Academic Affairs, School of Education

Associate Professor, Division of Educational Psychology & Methodology

Email handrade@albany.edu

Phone (518) 437-4422

Address ED 210, School of Education

University at Albany 1400 Western Ave Albany, NY 12222

Joan Newman, Ph.D.

Director & Associate Professor, Division of Educational Psychology & Methodology

Email joanewman@gmail.com

Phone (518) 442-4781

Address ED 236, School of Education

University at Albany 1400 Western Ave Albany, NY 12222